阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science!
前两集里我们尝试了用高级编程语言编程
Over the past two episodes, we got our first taste of programming in a high-level language,
例如Python或Java
like Python or Java.
我们还说到了不同的编程语言语句 比如赋值语句
We talked about different types of programming language statements – like assignments,
IF语句和循环语句 以及把语句放进函数 从而能执行计算
ifs, and loops – as well as putting statements into functions that perform a computation,
例如计算指数幂
like calculating an exponent.
重要的是我们写的计算指数幂的函数只是一种解决方法
Importantly, the function we wrote to calculate exponents is only one possible solution.
还有其他写这个函数的方法——使用不同的语句和顺序
There are other ways to write this function – using different statements in different orders
也能得到同样的数值结果
- that achieve exactly the same numerical result.
它们之间的差别就是算法
The difference between them is the algorithm,
算法是完成计算的特定步骤
that is the specific steps used to complete the computation.
有些算法优于其他 即使它们产生相同的结果
Some algorithms are better than others even if they produce equal results.
通常计算步骤越少 算法越好
Generally, the fewer steps it takes to compute, the better it is,
不过有时候我们考虑其他因素 如占用多少内存
though sometimes we care about other factors, like how much memory it uses.
算法这一术语来自于波斯博学家花拉子米
The term algorithm comes from Persian polymath Muhammad Ibn Mūsā Al-Khwārizmī who was
他是一千多年前代数的鼻祖
one of the fathers of algebra more than a millennium ago.
创造高效的算法这一早已存在于现代计算机之前的问题
The crafting of efficient algorithms, a problem that existed long before modern computers
引发了围绕计算的一整个学科
– led to a whole science surrounding computation,
接着进化成为现代的学科 没错 计算机科学
which evolved into the modern discipline of... you guessed it! Computer Science!
排序是最常涉及的一种算法
One of the most storied algorithmic problems in all of computer science is sorting
像是排序名字 数字
as in sorting names or sorting numbers.
计算机总是要排序
Computers sort all the time.
查询最便宜的机票 按最近时间排列电子邮件
Looking for the cheapest airfare, arranging your email by most recently sent,
按照姓氏展开通讯录 他们都需要排序
or scrolling your contacts by last name - those all require sorting.
你可能会想 排序不那么难 能有多少种算法
You might think “sorting isn't so tough... how many algorithms can there possibly be?”
答案是：很多
The answer is: a lot.
计算机学家花了几十年发明排序的算法
Computer Scientists have spent decades inventing algorithms for sorting,
这些算法有一些炫酷的名字比如冒泡排序 意大利面排序
with cool names like Bubble Sort and Spaghetti Sort.
我们试一下排序
Let's try sorting!
假设我们有一组去印第安纳波利斯的机票价格
Imagine we have a set of airfare prices to Indianapolis.
我们下周会说到这样的数据如何在内存中表示 不过现在
We'll talk about how data like this is represented in memory next week, but for now,
这样一系列的事物叫做数组
a series of items like this is called an array.
让我们看看这些数字以决定如何程序化地排序
Let's take a look at these numbers to help see how we might sort this programmatically.
一开始采用一个简单的算法
We'll start with a simple algorithm.
首先向下扫描数组找到最小的数字
First, let's scan down the array to find the smallest number.
最上面的是307
Starting at the top with 307.
目前只看到它一个 所以是最小的
It's the only number we've seen, so it's also the smallest.
下一个是239 它比307小 于是成为新的最小数字
The next is 239, that's smaller than 307, so it becomes our new smallest number.
下一个是214 新的最小数字
Next is 214, our new smallest number.
250不是 后面的384 299 312也都不是
250 is not, neither is 384, 299, 223 or 312.
这样我们结束了扫描所有的数字 得到最小数字214
So we've finished scanning all numbers, and 214 is the smallest.
为了按升序排列 把214和顶端的数字交换
To put this into ascending order, we swap 214 with the number in the top location.
好的 我们整理好了第一个数字
Great. We sorted one number!
现在重复同样的步骤 不过不是从最顶端开始
Now we repeat the same procedure, but instead of starting at the top,
我们可以从下一个开始
we can start one spot below.
首先是239 作为新一轮的最小数字
First we see 239, which we save as our new smallest number.
扫描余下的数组 发现223是第二最小的
Scanning the rest of the array, we find 223 is the next smallest,
于是把它和第二个位置的数字交换
so we swap this with the number in the second spot.
再次重复 从第三个数字往下扫描
Now we repeat again, starting from the third number down.
这一次 交换239和307
This time, we swap 239 with 307.
这个过程一直持续到确定最后一个数字
This process continues until we get to the very last number, and voila,
瞧 数组就排序好了 你可以预定去印第安纳波利斯的机票了
the array is sorted and you're ready to book that flight to Indianapolis!
刚才的过程只是排序的一种方法 一种算法
The process we just walked through is one way - or one algorithm - sorting an array.
它叫做选择排序 非常基础
It's called Selection Sort - and it's pretty basic.
这是选择算法的伪代码
Here's the pseudo-code.
这个函数可以排序8个 80个 或是8千万个数字
This function can be used to sort 8, 80, or 80 million numbers
一旦写出了函数 就可以反复使用
- and once you've written the function, you can use it over and over again.
这个算法里 我们从上到下遍历每一个位置
With this sort algorithm, we loop through each position in the array, from top to bottom,
对每一个位置都要遍历一遍数列
and then for each of those positions, we have to loop through the array
找到最小的数字然后交换位置
to find the smallest number to swap.
代码展示了这个过程 FOR循环里嵌套了另一个FOR循环
You can see this in the code, where one FOR loop is nested inside of another FOR loop.
这表明 简单来说如排序N个事物就要循环N次
This means, very roughly, that if we want to sort N items, we have to loop N times,
每一次循环里再循环N次 总计大约NxN或N的平方次
inside of which, we loop N times, for a grand total of roughly N times N loops Or N squared.
输入数据的大小与算法运行的步数之间的关系
This relationship of input size to the number of steps the algorithm takes to run
刻画了选择排序算法的复杂度
characterizes the complexity of the Selection Sort algorithm.
给出了算法速度快慢的估计
It gives you an approximation of how fast, or slow, an algorithm is going to be.
计算机学家把这个增长阶数认真地写成
Computer Scientists write this order of growth in something known as - no joke -
大O符号
“big O notation”.
N平方不是特别高效
N squared is not particularly efficient.
我们的例子数组中n=8 8的平方是64
Our example array had n = 8 items, and 8 squared is 64.
如果把规模从8增加到80
If we increase the size of our array from 8 items to 80,
运行时间就会是80的平方——6,400
the running time is now 80 squared, which is 6,400.
所以即使数组只增长了10倍 从8到80
So although our array only grew by 10 times - from 8 to 80
运行时间却增加了100倍 从64到6,400
- the running time increased by 100 times - from 64 to 6,400!
当数组更大时这一现象会被放大
This effect magnifies as the array gets larger.
对谷歌这样的大公司会是很大的问题
That's a big problem for a company like Google,
谷歌需要排序数百万至数十亿的条目
which has to sort arrays with millions or billions of entries.
你可能会问 作为不断成长的计算机学家
So, you might ask, as a burgeoning computer scientist,
有没有更高效的排序算法
is there a more efficient sorting algorithm?
让我们回到原来未排序的数组 尝试另一个不同的算法 归并算法
Let's go back to our old, unsorted array and try a different algorithm, merge sort.
归并算法的第一步是检查数组大小是否大于1
The first thing merge sort does is check if the size of the array is greater than 1.
如果大于1 就将数组分平分
If it is, it splits the array into two halves.
我们的数组长度是8 它分为两个长度为4的数组
Since our array is size 8, it gets split into two arrays of size 4.
这两个数组仍大于1 于是再次拆分 形成长度为2的数组
These are still bigger than size 1, so they get split again, into arrays of size 2,
最后他们分裂成8个长度为1的数组
and finally they split into 8 arrays with 1 item in each.
现在开始合并 这是归并排序名字的由来
Now we are ready to merge, which is how “merge sort” gets its name.
从前面两个数组开始 分别看它们的第一个 其实也是唯一一个数字
Starting with the first two arrays, we read the first - and only - value in them,
在这里 307和239
in this case, 307 and 239.
239更小 于是把它放在第一位
239 is smaller, so we take that value first.
唯一剩下的数字是307 那么把它放在第二位
The only number left is 307, so we put that value second.
我们成功合并了两个数组
We've successfully merged two arrays.
接着重复这个过程合并后面的数组对 按大小排列
We now repeat this process for the remaining pairs, putting them each in sorted order.
然后重复合并的步骤
Then the merge process repeats.
同样的处理前两个数组 比较各自的第一个数字
Again, we take the first two arrays, and we compare the first numbers in them.
这一次是239和214
This time its 239 and 214.
214更小 所以先取出它
214 is lowest, so we take that number first.
然后再比较两个数组的第一个数 230和250
Now we look again at the first two numbers in both arrays: 239 and 250.
239更小 于是接下来取出它
239 is lower, so we take that number next.
再后面两个：307和250
Now we look at the next two numbers: 307 and 250.
250更小 取出来
250 is lower, so we take that.
最后剩下307 把它加到后面
Finally, we're left with just 307, so that gets added last.
每一次 我们从两个数组开始 每个都已各自排序好
In every case, we start with two arrays, each individually sorted,
然后把他们合并为一个更大的排序好的数组
and merge them into a larger sorted array.
对剩下两个长度为2的数组重复相同的合并过程
We repeat the exact same merging process for the two remaining arrays of size two.
现在有个两个排序好的长度为4的数组
Now we have two sorted arrays of size 4.
跟前面一样合并它们 比较每个数组的第一个数字
Just as before, we merge, comparing the first two numbers in each array,
取出较小的
and taking the lowest.
重复这一过程直到所有数字都合并 这样数组就再次完全排序好了
We repeat this until all the numbers are merged, and then our array is fully sorted again!
坏消息是：无论我们排序了多少次
The bad news is: no matter how many times we sort these, you're still going to have
你仍然必须花214美元飞到印第安纳波利斯
to pay $214 to get to Indianapolis.
无论如何 归并排序的计算复杂度“大O”是N x Log N
Anyway, the “Big O” computational complexity of merge sort is N times the Log of N.
N来自需要比较合并元素的次数
The N comes from the number of times we need to compare and merge items,
它正比于数组中元素的个数
which is directly proportional to the number of items in the array.
Log N来自于合并的步数
The Log N comes from the number of merge steps.
我们的例子中 8个元素的数组被分解成4个的 然后2个的 最后1个的
In our example, we broke our array of 8 items into 4, then 2, and finally 1.
是3词分解
That's 3 splits.
这样对半分解的次数
Splitting in half repeatedly like this has a logarithmic relationship
是元素个数的对数 相信我
with the number of items - trust me!
8的以2为底的对数等于3
Log base 2 of 8 equals 3 splits.
如果增加元素个数到16 即两倍于原来的个数
If we double the size of our array to 16 - that's twice as many items to sort
分解次数只增加1 因为16的以2为底的对数等于4
- it only increases the number of split steps by 1 since log base 2 of 16 equals 4.
即使增大数组长度超过一千倍
Even if we increase the size of the array more than a thousand times,
从8到8,000个元素 分解步数仍旧很低
from 8 items to 8000 items, the number of split steps stays pretty low.
8000的以2为底的对数大约是13
Log base 2 of 8000 is roughly 13.
变大了 但比3大不了多少 大约4倍
That's more, but not much more than 3 - about four times larger
所以我们可以排序更多的数字
- and yet we're sorting a lot more numbers.
归并算法比选择算法高效得多
For this reason, merge sort is much more efficient than selection sort.
现在我可以更快地按照名字排列我的陶瓷猫收藏
And now I can put my ceramic cat collection in name order MUCH faster!
真的有几十种算法可以概述
There are literally dozens of sorting algorithms we could review, but instead,
不过我想继续说其他我喜欢的经典算法问题类型
I want to move on to my other favorite category of classic algorithmic problems:
图的遍历
graph search!
图是用边连接的顶点的网络
A graph is a network of nodes connected by lines.
你可以把它想象为一个地图 有城市和之间的道路
You can think of it like a map, with cities and roads connecting them.
城市间的道路需要花不同的时间
Routes between these cities take different amounts of time.
我们可以用花费或权重标识每条边
We can label each line with what is called a cost or weight.
在这里 是旅行花费的周数
In this case, it's weeks of travel.
假设我们想为驻扎在高庭的军队找到最快的路线
Now let's say we want to find the fastest route for an army at Highgarden
到临冬城的城堡
to reach the castle at Winterfell.
最简单的方法是尝试遍每一条路线
The simplest approach would just be to try every single path exhaustively
并计算每一条路线的总花费
and calculate the total cost of each.
那是一种暴力的方法
That's a brute force approach.
我们本可以用暴力法排序
We could have used a brute force approach in sorting,
即系统地尝试每一个数组的排列并检查是否有序
by systematically trying every permutation of the array to check if it's sorted.
这回是N的阶乘的复杂度 阶乘是定点数
This would have an N factorial complexity - that is the number of nodes,
乘上它减1 再乘上它减2 这样直到1
times one less, times one less than that, and so on until 1.
这比N平方更缓慢
Which is way worse than even N squared.
不过我们有更精巧的方法
But, we can be way more clever!
解决图的遍历经典的算法是
The classic algorithmic solution to this graph problem was invented
计算机科学理论与实践的大神 艾兹格·迪科斯彻发明的
by one of the greatest minds in computer science practice and theory, Edsger Dijkstra,
这也合理的命名为迪科斯彻算法
so it's appropriately named Dijkstra's algorithm.
高庭开始时花费0周
We start in Highgarden with a cost of 0, which we mark inside the node.
往后 把其他城市用问号标注
For now, we mark all other cities with question marks
因为还不知道到那里的花费
- we don't know the cost of getting to them yet.
迪科斯彻算法总是从最低花费的顶点开始
Dijkstra's algorithm always starts with the node with lowest cost.
在这里 只有一个顶点高庭 所以从这里开始
In this case, it only knows about one node, Highgarden, so it starts there.
然后跟踪一步就到达的顶点的道路
It follows all paths from that node to all connecting nodes that are one step away,
并记录到每一个顶点的花费
and records the cost to get to each of them.
算法的一轮就结束了
That completes one round of the algorithm.
我们还没有到达临冬城 所以循环再次运行迪科斯彻算法
We haven't encountered Winterfell yet, so we loop and run Dijkstra's algorithm again.
高庭已经经过了 下一个最低的是君临城
With Highgarden already checked, the next lowest cost node is King's Landing.
跟前面一样 跟踪每个未经过的路去到相连的城市
Just as before, we follow every unvisited line to any connecting cities.
去往三叉戟的路花费5周
The line to The Trident has a cost of 5.
不过我们要记录的是从高庭来的连续花费
However, we want to keep a running cost from Highgarden,
所以到三叉戟的总花费是8+5即13周
so the total cost of getting to the Trident is 8 plus 5, which is 13 weeks.
现在沿着另一条路到奔流城 花费时间高达25周 共33周
Now we follow the offroad path to Riverrun, which has a high cost of 25, for a total of 33.
但是可以看到奔流城已经有了一条道路
But we can see inside of Riverrun that we've already found a path
花费更低只是10周
with a lower cost of just 10.
所以舍弃新路径 仍用原来更好的路
So we disregard our new path, and stick with the previous, better path.
我们检查了所有从君临城出发的路 没有到达临冬城的
We've now explored every line from King's Landing and didn't find Winterfell,
我们继续
so we move on.
接下来最低花费的顶点是奔流城 10周
The next lowest cost node is Riverrun, at 10 weeks.
先查看去三叉戟的道路 总共花费10＋2 12周
First we check the path to The Trident, which has a total cost of 10 plus 2, or 12.
比之前13周的路径稍微快一些
That's slightly better than the previous path we found, which had a cost of 13,
所以更新到三叉戟的路径和花费
so we update the path and cost to The Trident.
奔流城还有一条通往派克城的路花费3周
There is also a line from Riverrun to Pyke with a cost of 3.
10+3 13 优于原来的花费14
10 plus 3 is 13, which beats the previous cost of 14,
于是同样的更新派克城的路径和花费
and so we update Pyke's path and cost as well.
从奔流城的所有道路都检查过了 你猜对了
That's all paths from Riverrun checked... so... you guessed it,
迪科斯彻算法再次循环
Dijkstra's algorithm loops again.
下一个最低花费的顶点是三叉戟
The node with the next lowest cost is The Trident
三叉戟出发的唯一没检查的路是去临冬城的
and the only line from The Trident that we haven't checked is a path to Winterfell!
花费10周 再加上到三叉戟的12周
It has a cost of 10, plus we need to add in the cost of 12 it takes to get to The Trident,
总共是22周
for a grand total cost of 22.
检查最后的路径从派克城到临冬城 总共31周
We check our last path, from Pyke to Winterfell, which sums to 31.
我们得到了最低的总花费和最快的路径
Now we know the lowest total cost, and also the fastest route
军队绕过君临城到达临冬城
for the army to get there, which avoids King's Landing!
迪科斯彻原创的算法与1956年提出
Dijkstra's original algorithm, conceived in 1956,
复杂度是图中定点数的平方
had a complexity of the number of nodes in the graph squared.
我们已经说过平方并不高效
And squared, as we already discussed, is never great, because it means
因为这个算法不能扩展到更大的问题 如美国的公路地图
the algorithm can't scale to big problems - like the entire road map of the United States.
幸运的是 迪科斯彻算法几年后得到了改进
Fortunately, Dijkstra's algorithm was improved a few years later
复杂度是顶点数乘顶点数的对数
to take the number of nodes in the graph, times the log of the number of nodes,
加上边的条数
PLUS the number of lines.
尽管看上去复杂一些 它确实更快
Although this looks more complicated, it's actually quite a bit faster.
代入示例的图来证明 有6个城市和9条路
Plugging in our example graph, with 6 cities and 9 lines, proves it.
算法复杂度从36步下降到约14
Our algorithm drops from 36 loops to around 14.
跟排序一样 图的遍历也有许多算法
As with sorting, there are innumerable graph search algorithms,
有着各自的优缺点
with different pros and cons.
你用谷歌地图查找线路时
Every time you use a service like Google Maps to find directions, an algorithm
服务器会运行迪科斯彻类似的算法给你找出最好的路线
much like Dijkstra's is running on servers to figure out the best route for you.
算法随处可见 现代社会必不可少
Algorithms are everywhere and the modern world would not be possible without them.
这一集我们只接触了算法的冰山一角
We touched only the very tip of the algorithmic iceberg in this episode,
计算机科学家的核心任务是平衡现有的算法
but a central part of being a computer scientist is leveraging existing algorithms
并根据需要写出新的算法
and writing new ones when needed,
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
希望这个小小的体验能激发你进一步探索的兴趣
and I hope this little taste has intrigued you to SEARCH further.
下周见
I'll see you next week.